Thank you.
Krishnamurti, in dialogue with Dr. Alan W. Anderson.
J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England.
For the past 40 years, he has been speaking in the
United States, Europe, India, Australia, and other parts of the world.
From the outset of his life's work, he
repudiated all connections with organized religions and ideologies,
and said that his only concern
was to set men absolutely unconditionally free.
He is the author of many books, among them The Awakening of Intelligence,
The Urgency of Change, Freedom from the Known, and The Flight of the Eagle.
This is one of a series of
dialogues between Krishnamurti and Dr. Alan W. Anderson,
who is professor of religious
studies at San Diego State University,
where he teaches Indian and Chinese scriptures,
and the oracular tradition.
Dr. Anderson, a published poet, received his degree
from Columbia University and the Union Theological Seminary.
He has been honored with a Distinguished
Teaching Award from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, in this series of conversations,
we've been exploring the general
question of the transformation of man,
a transformation which, as you
say, is not dependent on knowledge,
but on the ability to understand the world.
And as I recall, we arrived
at a point that was very crucial,
namely the one concerned
with relationship and communication.
I remember one point in our conversation
together that was extremely instructive for me,
a point at which, when you asked
me a question, I began to answer it,
and you interrupted me, and reminded the viewers and me,
Dr. Anderson, a published poet, who was a
professor of religious studies at San Diego State University,
that the important thing here is
not to finish out of theoretical construction,
rather to attain to the right beginning point,
so that we don't go
beyond where we haven't yet begun.
This, as I repeat, was extremely instructive for me,
and I was thinking, if it's agreeable with you,
that it would be helpful today if we could
begin at the point of a concern for communication.
And relationship.
To go into that question, begin to unravel it.
Unravel it, quite.
I wonder, sir, what that word communication means.
To communicate implies not only verbally,
but also
the
listening,
in which there is a sharing,
a thinking together,
not accepting something that you or I say,
but sharing together, thinking together, creating together,
all that is involved in that word communicate.
And
in that word,
in that word is implied also the art of listening.
The art of listening
demands a quality of attention
in which there is real listening,
real sense of having an insight
as we go along.
Yes.
It's second,
not at the end, but at the beginning.
So that we are
together, walking together all the time.
Yes, yes.
Right.
There's a concurrent activity here.
Not one making a statement, the other thinking about it,
and then saying, well, I agree, I don't agree,
I accept, I don't accept, these
are the reasons I don't accept,
these are the reasons I do.
But we are walking together.
Walking, journeying together,
walking together on the same path.
Side by side.
Yes.
On the same road, with the same attention,
with the same intensity, at the same time.
Otherwise there is no communication.
Exactly. Exactly.
Communication implies there must be
at the same level, at the same time,
with the same intensity, we are walking together.
We are thinking together, we are observing together,
sharing together.
Would you say that this requires an activity
that underlies the speaking together,
or does one come to the activity
after one has started to speak together?
No, sir, we are not saying
what is the art of listening.
Aren't we?
Yes.
The art of listening implies, doesn't it,
that there is not only the verbal understanding
between you and me,
because we are both speaking English,
and we know the meaning
of each word, more or less,
and at the same time
we are sharing the problem together,
sharing the issue together.
Because, as you said, it is
a matter of life and death.
Absolutely.
If you and I are both
serious, we are sharing the thing.
So, in communication,
there is not only a verbal communication,
but there is a non-verbal communication,
which is really what is
the meaning of life and death.
Which comes into being,
or which happens when one has the art
of really listening to somebody,
in which there is no acceptance, no denial,
or comparison, or judgement,
just the act of listening.
I wonder whether I am on the right track here,
if I suggest that there is a relation
that is very deep here between communication
and what we call in English, communion.
Communion, yes.
So that if we are in communion,
our chance of communicating...
Becomes simpler. Right.
Now, to be in communion with each other,
we must have...
both of us must be serious about the same problem.
At the same time,
we must have the same passion,
otherwise there is no communication.
Exactly.
If you are not interested in what is being said,
well, you will think of something else
and communication stops.
So, there is a verbal communication
and a non-verbal communication.
They are both operating at the same time.
One doesn't precede the other,
or follow upon the other.
It is...
Yes. They move together.
Which means that each of us, being serious,
give our attention completely to the issue.
That act of seriousness that takes place
then requires the utmost devoted attention.
Sir, but... Yes.
A man who is really serious lives.
Not the man who is flippant
or merely wanting to be entertained.
He doesn't live.
The general notion of being serious about something
generally suggests either undergoing some pain
about something,
or I am serious about something
in order to get something else.
These two things, as a rule,
are what persons imagine by seriousness.
As a matter of fact, we often hear this expression,
don't look so serious.
Yes. Don't we?
Yes.
It is as though we fear something about the serious.
Sir, look, as we said yesterday,
the world is in a mess.
Yes.
And it is my responsibility, living in this world,
as a human being who has created this mess,
it is my responsibility to be serious
in the resolution of this problem.
I am serious. It doesn't mean I am long-faced,
I am miserable, unhappy, or
I want something out of it.
It has got to be solved.
It is like going... If one has cancer,
one is serious about it,
you don't play around with it.
Action in relation to the seriousness, then,
is instantaneous.
Obviously. Yes.
This raises not an additional question.
I don't mean to go beyond where we haven't begun,
in that sense,
but time assumes for the serious person
something very different for his undergoing
than it would seem to be for the unserious person.
One wouldn't have, then, the
feeling of something being dragged out,
or, as we say in English,
time that has to be put in.
Put in, quite.
As a matter of fact, one, in this concurrent communication,
in which communion,
is abidingly present.
Time as such would not in any way oppress.
No, sir. No, sir.
Am I...? Quite right.
But you see, sir,
I am trying to see
what it means to be serious.
The intent,
the urge,
the feeling of total responsibility,
the feeling of action, the doing,
not, I will do.
All that is implied in that word seriousness.
At least I put all those things into that word.
But, sir,
could we look for a moment at one of them
that you put into them, responsibility,
able to be responsive?
That's right. To respond adequately.
Yes, to respond adequately.
To any challenge.
The challenge now is that
the world is in a mess,
confusion, sorrow and every...
violent, all that.
I must, as a human
being who has created this thing,
I must respond adequately.
The adequacy depends on my seriousness in that sense,
on my observation of the chaos,
and responding not according to my prejudices,
my inclination or tendencies, or pleasures or fears,
but responding to the problem,
not according to my translation of the problem.
Yes, I'm just thinking, as you are speaking,
about how difficult it is to...
to communicate this to the person who is thinking
that the way adequately to respond to this chaos
is to have a plan for
it, which one superimposes on it.
And that's exactly what we assume.
And if the plan doesn't work out, we blame ourselves...
Or change the plan.
Or we change the plan, yes.
But we don't respond to the challenge.
No.
We respond according to our conclusion about the problem.
Exactly.
Therefore it means really, sir,
if you can explore it a little more,
the observer is the observed.
Therefore the change, if it comes, is total.
Yes, that's right.
Not partial.
One is no longer outside what he is operating upon.
That's right.
And what he is operating upon is not outside himself.
Because, as we said yesterday,
it's very interesting, if we go into it rather deeply,
the world is me, I am the world.
That's not an intellectual or emotional, but a fact.
Now, when I approach this,
the problem, the chaos, the misery, the suffering,
the violence and all that,
I approach it with my conclusions,
with my fears, with my despairs.
I don't look at the problem.
Well, would you think it
possible to put it this way,
that one doesn't make room for the problem?
Yes, yes, put it in a way...
Would that be all right?
Yes.
One day there is...
Sir, let's look at this.
I have...
As a human being, one has created this misery,
which is called the society in which we live,
an immoral society.
Oh, yes.
Completely immoral.
As a human being, one has created that.
But that human being, looking at it, separates himself
and says, I must do something about it.
The it is me.
Some people respond to that this way.
They say, well, look,
if I...
I'm truly serious, I'm truly responsible,
I make this act,
and there comes between me and the world
this confluent relationship,
which is total.
All the things that are going
on out there that are atrocious,
let's say, 2500 miles away
from where I am, don't stop.
Therefore, how can I stop?
How can I say that the whole world is me
and I am the whole world?
This objection comes up again and again.
I'm interested to know what
your reply to that would be.
Sir, look,
we are human beings irrespective of our labels
– English, French, German, all the rest of it.
Mm-hm.
A human being living in America or in India
has the problems of relationship, of suffering,
of jealousy, envy, greed, ambition, imitation, conformity,
and all that are our
problems, common to both of us.
Yes.
And when I say the
world is me and the world...
me is the world and the world I am,
I see that as a reality, not as a concept.
Mm-hm.
Now, my responsibility to the challenge,
to be adequate,
must be not in terms of what I think,
but what the problem is.
Mm-hm.
Yes, I follow you, I'm sure, here.
I was thinking while you were saying that
that it might have been possible
to answer the question that I posed,
and I'm posing the question simply because
I know some persons who might very well view this
who would raise that and want to participate
with us in this conversation.
I wondered,
whether you might have said that
as soon as one puts it that way,
one has already divorced himself...
That's right.
...from the issue.
That in the practical order,
that question is an interposition
that simply does not have a place
in the activity that you are talking about.
Yes, that's right.
Now, this is very interesting,
because it means that the
person must suspend his disbelief...
Or his belief.
Yes.
And observe the thing.
Which is not possible
if the observer is different from the observed.
Now, would you explore the practical aspect
of this with me for a moment?
People will say,
who up to this point are listening,
it would seem,
people at this point will say,
well, yes, but I can't stop it.
I think I have...
I have an intuition of what you mean, they'll say.
But the minute that I open myself,
or begin to open myself,
all these things seem to rush in on me.
What I had hoped doesn't seem to take place.
If I understand you correctly,
they are really not doing what they claim
that they are trying to do.
That's right.
Sir, can we put this question differently?
What is a human being to do,
confronted with this problem of suffering, chaos,
all that is going on round us?
Yes.
What is he to do?
He approaches it generally
with a conclusion,
what he should do about it.
And this conclusion is interposed between him...
Yes, the conclusion is the factor of separation.
Right.
Now, can he observe the fact of this confusion
without any conclusions?
Without any planning,
without any predetermined way
of getting out of this chaos?
Because his predetermined conclusions,
ideas and so on,
are all derived from the past.
And the past is trying to resolve the problem.
Yes, yes.
And therefore he is translating it
and acting according to his previous conclusions,
whereas the fact demands that you look at it.
The fact demands that you observe it,
that you listen to it.
The fact itself will have the answer,
you don't have to bring the answer to it.
I wonder if I am making myself clear.
Yes, I am listening very, very hard.
I really am.
I am afraid if I am not going beyond
where I shouldn't, haven't yet begun,
the next question that would naturally arise here
or perhaps you might feel when I raise the question
that it is the wrong question.
But can one communicate
in the sense that we have been unravelling this?
One says, I don't know.
It doesn't seem to me that I have done this.
One says, I haven't done this yet.
I can recognise all the things
that have been described that are terrible.
I don't recognise all the things
that appear to be promised
without suggesting that I am imagining them
or projecting them out there.
Clearly, if there is to be a change,
it has to be a change that is altogether radical.
Yes.
Now, I must start. What do I do?
Sir, there are two things involved, aren't there?
Yes.
First, I must learn from the problem,
which means I must have a mind
that has a quality of humility.
It doesn't come to a
sense, I know all about it.
What he knows is merely explanations,
rational or irrational.
He comes to the problem
with rational or irrational solutions.
Therefore he is not learning from the problem.
The problem will reveal an infinite lot of things
if I am capable of looking
at it and learning about it.
And for that I must have a sense of humility.
I am saying, I don't know.
This is a tremendous problem, let me look at it,
let me learn about it,
not I come to it with my conclusions.
Therefore I will stop learning about the problem.
Are you suggesting that this act
is a waiting on the problem to reveal itself?
That's right.
Therefore I must be capable of looking at it.
I cannot look at it if
I come to it with ideas,
with ideations, with mentations,
of all very kind and conclusions.
I must come to it
and say, look, what is it?
Not learn, I must learn from it,
not learn according to some professor,
some psychologist, some philosopher.
That one has the capacity for this.
Some persons would suggest.
I don't give a... Sir, we are so vain.
But this doesn't mean anything for the doing
of what must be done, that there is a capacity.
No. The learning is the doing.
Exactly. Yes, yes.
I wanted to make that clear because we comfort ourselves
with the curious notion, if I've been following you,
that we possess a possibility,
and because we possess the possibility
we think that some day it will actualise itself, perhaps.
Quite, quite.
But if I'm correct both ways,
no possibility can actualise itself,
and in the practical order that never occurs.
But somehow it's believed, isn't it?
I'm afraid it is. It is believed.
Sir, it is really quite simple.
There is this misery, confusion,
immense sorrow in the world, violence, all that.
I have... human beings have created it.
Human beings have built a structure of society
which sustains this chaos.
That's a fact.
Now, I come to it,
a human being comes to it,
trying to resolve it according to his plan,
according to his prejudices,
his instincts,
his idiosyncrasies or knowledge.
Why?
Which means he has already understood the problem.
Whereas the problem is always new.
So I must come to it afresh.
One of the things that has concerned me
for many, many years as a reader,
as a student,
as one whose daily work
involves the study of scriptures,
is the recurrent statement
that one comes upon,
sometimes in a very dramatic form.
Take the prophetic ministry of Jesus,
where he speaks,
and he says that they are hearing,
but they are not listening.
They are observing,
but they are not seeing.
And doing.
But then...
it seems...
that he doesn't say,
in order to attain to that,
do this.
No, the closest he comes to it
is through the analogy with the child,
to have faith as a little child.
Now, I don't want to talk about words here,
because that would be disastrous.
So what's meant by faith here?
What's meant by faith here is not something
that perhaps we would probably go into.
But the analogy with the child
suggests that the child is doing something
that is lost somewhere along the way,
in some respect.
I'm sure he didn't mean that there's a perfect continuity
between the adult and the child.
But there's...
Why is it, over the centuries,
that men have said this over and over again,
namely, you're not listening,
you're not seeing,
and then they don't point to an operation,
they point to an analogy,
and then some of them
don't even point to an analogy,
they just hold up a flower.
Sir, look, we live on words.
Most people live on words.
They don't go beyond the word.
And what we are talking about
is not only the word,
the meaning of the word,
the communication that exists in using words,
but the non-verbal communication
which is having an insight.
That's what we are talking
about all the time, so far.
Yes.
That is, the mind can only have an insight
if it is capable of listening.
And you may say,
you do listen when the
crisis is right at your doorstep.
Now, I think I'm at
a point here that is solid.
Yes.
Solid.
Is it that we don't allow ourselves
access to the crisis
that's there continuously?
It isn't a crisis that's episodic.
No, crisis is always there.
Right, right.
Well, we are doing something
to shut ourselves off from it, aren't we?
Or we don't know how to meet it.
We don't know, either we avoid it,
or we don't know how to meet it,
or we are indifferent,
we have become so callous.
All these three are involved
in not facing the crisis.
Because I'm frightened.
One is frightened.
One says, my lord,
I don't know how to deal with it.
So one goes off to an analyst,
or to a priest,
or picks up a book to
see how it can be translated.
He becomes irresponsible.
Or sometimes people will register the disappointment
that things haven't worked out.
So why try something new?
And this would be a buffer.
That's what I mean.
Avoidance, there are so many ways to avoid.
Clarity.
Whatever, cunning, superficial,
and very subtle,
all that is involved in avoiding an issue.
So what we are trying to say, sir, isn't it,
the observer is the past,
as we said yesterday.
Yes.
The observer is trying to translate
and act according to the past.
When the crisis arises.
The crisis is always new.
Otherwise it is not a crisis.
A challenge must be new, is new,
and always new.
But he translates it according to the past.
Now, can he look at that challenge,
that crisis,
without the response of the past?
May I read a sentence out of your book?
I think that maybe this has a very direct relationship
to what we are talking about.
It's a sentence that...
I have to take these things off to read it.
It's a sentence which arrested me when I read it.
Through negation,
that thing which alone is the positive,
comes into being.
May I read it again?
Yes, sir.
Through negation,
something is done, apparently.
Oh, absolutely.
Right, right.
So we are not leaving it at the point where
we are saying simply,
words are of no consequence,
therefore I will do something non-verbal,
or I will say something
because I never communicate with the non-verbal.
It has nothing to do with it.
Something must be done.
Absolutely.
There is an act.
Life is action.
Exactly.
It isn't just...
Now, here,
and I suppose I should
say for our listeners and viewers
that this is from
The Awakening of Intelligence,
I think the most recent publication,
of yours,
and it's on page 196,
in the chapter on freedom.
Through negation,
I take it that's a word for this act.
For this act.
That thing which alone is the positive,
the word alone came over to me
with the force of something unique.
Yes, sir.
Something that's not continuous with anything else.
That thing which alone
is the positive
comes into being.
There's no temporal hiatus here,
so we're back to that thing we began with
in our earlier conversations about
not being dependent on knowledge and time.
Could we look at this
negation together for a moment?
I have the feeling that
you have understood this correctly,
that unless this whatever it is
that's called negation
is not an abiding activity,
then communion and communication
and the relationship that we were talking about
just simply can never be reached.
Sir...
Is that correct?
Quite.
May I put it this way?
I must negate,
I mean, negate not intellectually or verbally,
actually negate the society in which I live.
The social...
the implication of immorality
which exists in society,
on which society is built,
I must negate totally that immorality.
That means I live morally.
In negating that,
the positive is the moral.
I don't know if I'm...
No, yes, no, I'm being quiet
because I want to follow step by step.
I don't want to go beyond where I've begun.
I negate totally the idea of success.
Yes, yes, I negate totally the idea...
Totally.
Yes.
Not only...
ええんで
mundane world, not only in the sense of achievement
in a world of money, position, authority,
I negate that completely.
And I also negate success in the so-called spiritual world.
Oh yes, quite the temptation.
Both are the same.
I call this spiritual and I call that physical, mundane.
So in negating success, achievement,
there comes an energy,
through negation there is a tremendous energy
to act totally differently,
which is not
in the field of success,
in the field of imitation, conformity and all that.
So through negation,
I mean actual negation, not just ideal negation,
through actual negation
of that which is immoral,
morality comes into being.
Which is altogether different from trying to be moral.
That's of course. Trying to be moral is immoral.
Yes.
May I try to go into this another step?
At least it would be a step for me.
There's something that I intuit here
as a double aspect to this negation.
I'd like very much to see whether this is
concurrent with your own feeling about this.
I was going to say statement, and I stopped myself.
My desire for success in itself
is a withholding myself from the problem
that we talked about.
And that itself is a form of negation.
I have negated access to myself.
I've negated the...
In other words, I have
done violence to what it is
that wishes to reveal itself.
Yes.
So I am going to negate
then my negation as the observer.
Yes.
So I am going to negate
then my negation as the observer.
Yes.
This I wanted to make sure.
We must be clear. Quite right, sir.
When we use the word
negate, as it is generally understood,
it's an act of violence.
Yes. That's what I was hoping I was...
It's an act of violence.
I negate.
I brush it aside.
Right.
We are using the word
negate not in the violent sense,
but the understanding,
the understanding of what success implies.
The understanding of what success implies.
The me who is separate from you,
wanting or desiring success
which will put me in
a position of authority, power, prestige.
So I am in negating
success, I am negating my desire to be powerful.
Uh-huh.
Which I negate only when I have understood
the whole process that's involved in achieving success.
In achieving success is employed ruthlessness,
Yes.
lack of love,
lack of immense,
immense consideration for others,
lack of...
and the sense of conformity, imitation,
accepting the social structure,
all that is involved,
and the understanding of all that,
when I negate success.
It is not an act of violence.
On the contrary, it's an act of tremendous attention.
I've negated something in my person.
I've negated myself.
Right. I've negated myself.
The me which is separate from you.
Exactly.
And therefore I've negated violence
which comes about when there is separation.
Would you use the term self-denial here?
Yes.
Self-denial here.
Here, not in the sense of how
it has been received down the line.
No.
But if there's anything to what
has been stated in the past,
could a person who saw that word, self-denial,
read that word in this context that you're using?
I'm afraid he wouldn't.
Self-denial means sacrifice, pain, lack of understanding.
But if he heard what you're saying...
Ah, then...
Why use another word when you have understood this thing?
Well, maybe he'd want to communicate with someone.
I would say, but change the word
so that we both understand the meaning of self-denial.
I mean, all religions have
based their action on self-denial.
So, sacrifice, deny your desire, deny
you are looking at a woman,
or deny riches, take a vow to poverty,
you know, all the vow of
poverty, vow of celibacy and so on.
All those are a kind of punishment,
a distorting of a clear perception.
If I see something clearly, the action is immediate.
So, deny... Sir, negate implies diligence.
The word, you know,
diligence means giving complete attention
to the fact of success.
Yes, we are taking that word.
Giving my whole attention to success,
in that attention the whole map of success is revealed.
With all its horrors.
With all the things involved in it.
And it is only then, the seeing is the doing,
then it's finished.
The mind can never revert to success,
and therefore become bitter, all the things that follow.
What you are saying, I take
it, is that once this happens...
It's finished.
...there is no reversion.
Of course not.
Say, for instance, sir...
It isn't something that one has to keep up.
Of course not.
Well, fine, I'm delighted we've established that.
But say, for instance, what happened in 1928,
I happened to be the head of a tremendous organisation,
a religious organisation,
and I saw around me various religious organisations,
sects, Catholic, Protestant,
and I see all trying to find truth.
I said, no organisation can lead man to truth.
So I dissolved it.
Property, an enormous business, all that.
I can never go back to it.
When you see something as poison,
you won't take it again.
You say, by Jove, I've made a mistake,
I should go back and...
It is, sir, it's like seeing danger.
When you see danger, you never go near it again.
I hope I won't annoy you
by talking about words here again.
But you know, so many
of the things that you say
cast a light on...
No, no.
...common terms which, for me at least, illuminate them.
They sound altogether different
from the way they used to be heard.
For instance, we say in English, don't we,
practice makes perfect.
Now, obviously, this...
this can't be the case if we mean by practice.
That we're repeating something.
But if we mean by practice,
the Greek praxis, which is concerned directly with act,
not repetition, but with act,
then to say it makes perfect
doesn't refer to time at all.
It's that upon the instant the act is performed,
perfection is.
Now, I'm sorry, but I used the word instant again.
And I understand why that's awkward.
But I think in our communication,
the concern for the word here
is one that surely is productive,
because one can open himself to a word.
And if one sees the word that way,
then it appears that there's a whole host
of phenomena which suddenly acquire
a very magical significance.
Not magical in the sense of enchantment,
but they open a door,
which when walked into
immediately situates him
in the crisis in such a way that
he attains to this that you call
the one alone,
the unique,
which comes into being.
So, sir, can we now go back
or go forward to the question
of freedom and responsibility in relationship?
That's what we left out yesterday.
Right.
Yes, and that was quoted from the chapter on freedom.
Yes.
First of all, can we go into this question
of what it is to be responsible?
I should like that.
Because I think that is
what we are missing in this world,
what is happening now.
We don't feel responsible.
We don't feel we are responsible because
the people in position,
in authority, politically, religiously,
are responsible. We are not.
That is the general feeling that's all over the world.
Those over there have been delegated
to do a job by me.
And scientists, politicians,
the educational people,
the religious people,
they are responsible,
but I know nothing about it, I just follow.
That is the general attitude
right through the world.
Oh, yes.
Solzhenitsyn, you follow the whole thing.
Yes, right.
One feels he gets off scot-free that way
because it is the other one's fault.
Yes. So, I make myself irresponsible.
By delegating responsibility to you,
I become irresponsible.
Whereas now we are saying
nobody is responsible except you.
Because you are the world,
the world is you.
You have created this mess,
you alone can bring about clarity.
Therefore you are totally, utterly,
completely responsible,
and nobody else.
Now, that means you have to be
a light to yourself,
not the light
of a professor, or an analyst,
or a psychologist,
or the light of Jesus,
or the light of the Buddha.
You have to be a light to yourself
in a world that is utterly becoming dark.
That means you have to be responsible.
Now, what does that word mean?
It means really,
to respond totally, adequately to every challenge.
You cannot possibly respond adequately
if you are rooted in the past.
Because the challenge is new,
otherwise it is not a challenge.
A crisis is new,
otherwise it is not a crisis.
So, if I respond to a crisis
in terms of a preconceived plan,
which the communists are doing,
or the Catholics, or the Protestants,
and so on, so on,
then they are not responding totally
and adequately to the challenge.
This takes me back to something
I think that is very germane
in the dramatic situation
of confrontation between
the soldier
and the Lord Krishna
in the Gita.
Arjuna, the general of the army,
says to Krishna,
tell me definitely what to do
and I will do it.
Now, Krishna doesn't turn around
and say to him in the next verse,
I am not going to tell you what to do.
But of course, at that point
he simply doesn't tell him what to do.
And one of the great Sanskrit scholars
has pointed out that
that is an irresponsible reaction
on the part of the teacher.
But if I am understanding you correctly,
he couldn't have done otherwise.
When that man put that question,
he is putting a question out of irresponsibility.
Of course. A refusal to be responsible.
Exactly. A refusal to be responsible.
That's why, sir,
responsibility means total commitment.
Total commitment.
Total commitment to the challenge.
Responding to the challenge
adequately, completely to a crisis.
That is, the word responsibility means that.
To respond.
I cannot respond completely if I am frightened.
Or I cannot respond completely
if I am seeking pleasure.
I cannot respond totally
if my action is routine,
is repetitive, is traditional, is conditioned.
So to respond adequately to a challenge means
the me, which is the past, must end.
And at this point, Arjuna,
the past wants it continued right down the line.
That's what everybody wants, sir.
Politically, look what is happening in this country
and elsewhere.
We don't feel responsible.
We don't feel responsible
to how we bring our children up.
I understand. I really do, I think.
In our next conversation,
I'd really like to continue this
in terms of the phrase that we sometimes use,
being responsible for my action.
But that doesn't seem to be saying exactly
what you're saying at all.
As a matter of fact, it seems
to be quite wide of the mark.
Quite wide.
Good. Let's do that.